<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A complaint of the oppressed against the oppressors, or, The unjust and arbitrary proceedings of some souldiers and justices against some sober godly persons, in and near London who now lye in stinking goals [i.e. gaols] for the testimony of good conscience : with some reasons why they cannot swear allegiance to obtain their liberty / faithfully collected by John Lovewel.</title>
            <author>Lovewel, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11760857</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11760857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49310)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1486:53)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A complaint of the oppressed against the oppressors, or, The unjust and arbitrary proceedings of some souldiers and justices against some sober godly persons, in and near London who now lye in stinking goals [i.e. gaols] for the testimony of good conscience : with some reasons why they cannot swear allegiance to obtain their liberty / faithfully collected by John Lovewel.</title>
                  <author>Lovewel, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48684:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48684:1"/>
            <p>A Complaint OF THE OPPRESSED AGAINST OPPRESSORS.</p>
            <p>OR, THE Unjuſt and Arbitrary PROCEEDINGS of ſome Souldiers and Juſtices, againſt ſome Sober Godly Perſons, in and near <hi>London;</hi> who now lye in ſtinking Goals for the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p>With Some REASONS why they cannot <hi>Swear Allegiance,</hi> to obtain their <hi>Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully Collected by <hi>JOHN LOVEWEL,</hi> A conſtant Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of their <hi>Patience</hi> in <hi>Suffering,</hi> and of the <hi>Injuſtice</hi> of their <hi>Perſecutors.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zeph. 3.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wo to her that is filthy and polluted, to the oppreſſing City.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 33.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wo to thee that ſpoileſt, and waſt not ſpoiled; and dealeſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly, and they dealt not treacherouſly with thee: when thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoil, thou ſhalt be ſpoiled, and when thou ſhalt make an end to deal treacherouſly, they ſhall deal treacherouſly with thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48684:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48684:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A COMPLAINT</hi> Of the OPPRESSED AGAINST OPPRESSORS.</head>
            <p>THe Unjuſt proceedings of ſome in preſent power, againſt many in this Nation, fearing God, cannot but be manifeſt to ſuch ſober men, that do or will take a view of the ſame. I having knowledge of the Sufferings of many Godly Perſons, eſpecially in and about <hi>London,</hi> whom their very adverſaries cannot blemiſh juſtly with the leaſt ſpot of Infamy, dare not but let the World know the Innocency of the men, and the Tyranny of their Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: And in what I ſhall ſay, I dare appeal to the Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of all ſober &amp; judicious perſons of what Perſwaſion ſoever, except the proud Prelate; Whether it be not Tyranny to the height, for men to be ſeized and taken out of their Beds at midnight by Souldiers, in a Hoſtile manner, with their Swords drawn, by means of which, their Wives and Children have been much affrighted, to their great detriment in point of health; and this done in a time of Peace, and without War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from any, no not ſo much as a Warrant from a Juſtice of the Peace. Others, taken from their peaceable Meetings, when they have been in the Lords ſervice in a publick manner, the doors being open for all that would, to ſee what they did, and hear what they ſaid. Others, attached as they have paſſed along the ſtreets about their lawful Imployments; and all this done by Souldiers without Warrant from any, and by them,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48684:3"/>carried before ſome men called Juſtices, but ſuch only in Name and Title, nothing ſo in truth. For <hi>They afflict the juſt, and they turn aſide the poor in the gate from their right,</hi> Amos 5.12. But leaving them a while, Reader take notice, that theſe Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to wit, one Liuetenant <hi>Wilton,</hi> a man very well known where he lives, (but not for any vertue he hath) and Enſigne <hi>Spike</hi> a man ſo well educated, that he ſcarce knows what Law or Religion is, and as to the buſineſs of a Souldier he is alſo a ſtranger, as I in charity judge of him: For theſe men, with the aſſiſtance of Serjeants and Souldiers, like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, have contracted that guilt upon themſelves, that had they known Law, been Religious, or Souldiers, they would have ſcorned to have defiled themſelves, ſo much as with a touch with a finger. But their actions have been ſuch as above ſaid, and how contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Laws of the Nation, I leave to the Judicious; and how li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able they are to be puniſhed by Law for their ſo doing, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Cap. 29. <hi>Anno 9.</hi> Hen. 3. ſaith, <hi>No free man ſhall be taken or impriſoned, or be diſſeized of his Free-hold, or Liberties, or free Cuſtoms, or be Out-lawed, or Exiled, or any ways Deſtroyed; nor we ſhall not paſs upon him, nor deal with him, but by the lawful judgement of his Peers, or by the Law of the Land; We ſhall not ſell to any man, we ſhall not deny nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre any man Right or Juſtice.</hi> Againe, <hi>No man of what eſtate or condition that he be, ſhall be put from his Land or Tenement, or taken, impriſoned, or diſ-inherited, or put to death, without being brought in to anſwer by due proceſs of Law. Anno</hi> 28. Ed. 3. Cap. 3. Thus he that hath but little ſight, may ſee how contrary to the good and wholſome Laws of the Nation theſe men have acted, and how diſhonourable it is to the King and his Government, for ſuch wicked Fellows to be ſuffered in ſuch arbitrary and villanous proceedings againſt ſober men, as they have from time to time practiſed. For if no man, of what eſtate or condition ſoever, ſhall be taken or Impriſoned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a due proceſs of the Law; then to ſeize any man without Warrant from ſome Miniſter of Juſtice, is to take and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon him at the Wills and Luſts of theſe baſe and inferior fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48684:3"/>who matter not the Honour of the King, the Violating of Law, nor the Liberty of the Subject; then will not theſe things cry loud to Heaven for Vengeance? Beſides theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinary fellows, cannot excuſe themſelves by pleading igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, for the King by open Proclamation, hath ſtrictly charged and commanded all Officers and Souldiers, and all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, that they ſhall not moleſt nor trouble any of his good Subjects, without Warrant or lawful Authority; as appears by his Proclamation, Intituled, <hi>A Proclamation prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting the Se zing of any perſons, or Searching Houſes, without Warrant, except in time of actual Inſurrection:</hi> Bearing date the <hi>ſeventeenth</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty. The which Proclamation (ſo much of it as is to our buſineſs in hand) I ſhall here inſert, for the better ſatisfaction of the Reader, as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And we being given to underſtand, that during thoſe late Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſeveral perſons have been impriſoned by Souldiers and others, their Houſes Searched, and their goods taken away, without law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Anthority, and that thereupon opprobrious words, and terms of diſcention, and diſcrimination of parties, have been uſed and given to Our great diſ-ſervice, contrary to the before ſaid Act of</hi> Pardon <hi>and</hi> Oblivion; <hi>and not withſtanding Our Royal pleaſure, ſo often publiſhed and declared to the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are therefore ſtrictly to charge and command all Officers and Souldiers, and all other Perſons whatſoever (unleſſe it be upon inevitable neceſſity of ſuddain and actual Rebellion and Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to forbear to moleſt or trouble any of our good Subjects, either in their Perſons or Eſtates, and not to preſume to Apprehend or Secure any Perſon or Perſons, or Seize any Armes what ſoever, or to ſearch any Houſes, without a lawful Warrant under the Hand and Seal of ſome one or more of the Lords of our Privy Council, or under the Hand and Seal of ſome one or more of the Lords Lieutenants, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty Lieutenants, or Juſtices of the Peace, in their reſpective Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Precincts, within the ſeveral Counties, Cities, and Towns Corporate, in our Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>and Town of</hi> Berwick upon Tweed. <hi>And we will that the ſaid Warrants be alwaies directed to ſome Conſtable or other known legal Officer, and that no Souldier do otherwiſe interpoſe or meddle with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48684:4"/>the Execution of the ſaid Warrants, then by aiding and aſſisting of the ſaid Conſtable, or other ſuch known legal Officer, or Officers as aforeſaid: and all Millitary Officers and Souldiers, are hereby com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be aiding and aſſiſting to ſuch Conſtable, or other legal Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, being by them or any of them thereunto required: And We do hereby declare, that aſ well all thoſe who ſhall hereafter be ſo hardy, as to offend againſt this Our Proclamation, ſhall not onely not receive Countenance from Us therein, but ſhall be left to be proceeded againſt according to Our Laws, and incurre Our high diſpleaſure, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons doing their utmoſt to bring Scandal and Contempt upon Our Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all which, there are theſe things Conſiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the King was very ſenſible of the great abuſes done to many by the illegal and lawleſs proceedings of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at that time, and the great diſ-ſervice they did him in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The King from the aforeſaid ſence, gives a ſtrict Charge and Command to all Officers and Souldiers, and all other Perſons, that they preſume not to Seize the perſon or perſons of any, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without Warrant under the Hand and Seals of ſuch mentioned in the Proclamation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That no Officer or Souldier is to meddle or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in the Execution of ſuch Warrant, if granted againſt any, except called by a Conſtable or other legal Officers, to their aſſiſtance in ſerving the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That the King will be ſo far from countenancing any that ſhall be ſo hardy as to offend againſt this his Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that they ſhall be left to be proceeded againſt accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Such perſons ſo offending, ſhall incurre his high diſpleaſure, as perſons doing their uttermoſt to bring Scandal and Contempt upon his Government.</p>
            <p>And yet theſe abovenamed men, would be thought to be high promoters of the Kings Honour and Government, when their actions (ſo declared to be by the King himſelf in his Proclamation) have been high and bold atempts made againſt, and Scandal to his Government.</p>
            <p>It is true, if drinking his Health in Bowles of Ale and Beer, and Glaſſes of Sack, till they become brutiſh, Swearing and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48684:4"/>Blaſpheming the holy Name of God, and ſuch like Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, will Honour the King and make his Government as famous as <hi>Solomons</hi> was, then they are the men that will do it. If their breaking his Laws, and abuſing the good People of the Land, as aboveſaid, will Honour him, they will do it: Such, as I take it, being all the Love to, or Valour they can ſhew for him or his Intereſt. But not to enlarge, I will now return to ſpeak of what Dealing theſe ſober men have ſound from the hands of theſe Juſtices. The Souldiers they ſeize contrary to Law, as you have heard, and away they carry them; it may be to <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> Lieutenant of the Tower, or <hi>Thomas Bide</hi> Ale-Brewer in <hi>Shoreditch,</hi> or ſome other man called a Juſtice, as the Souldiers pleaſe: And when they are before them, though no matter of Fact be laid to their charge; none accuſing them to their faces of the breach of any known Law; Seeing they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find any thing againſt them worthy of Bonds, they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to this point; <hi>Will you take the Oath of Allegïance;</hi> If any refuſe, they ſend him away to Goal, pretending great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters againſt them, which they inſert in their Mittimus in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, as dangerous perſons, Plotting, ſpeaking Treaſon, and the like: Which he that knows any thing in Law, knows that a general Charge is no Charge; the Law requiring, <hi>That no free born Engliſh-man be kept in durance without ſome particular Charge be expreſſed in the Warrant, by which he is committed and held.</hi> By which it is manifeſt, that theſe Juſtices have as little regard to the Honour of the King, as the Souldiers; For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by Law, they ought to rebuke and puniſh thoſe Souldiers, that ſo illegally ſeize the perſons of theſe civil men, they juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their unwarrantable doing, and in ſtead thereof commit the poor men to priſon, contrary to Law alſo; making no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch arbitrary actions, but willingly ſwallow them. And further it is evident, That no one Juſtice hath power to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Oath to any, though ſome of them will not ſtick to do it (for I my ſelf was in place, when <hi>Thomas Bide</hi> miniſtred the Oath to two perſons, and never a Juſtice there but himſelf, making them manifeſtly forſwear themſelves) contrary to the expreſſe letter of the Law, which enables no one Juſtice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any perſon to take the Oath, much leſſe to miniſter it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48684:5"/>to any: For ſaith the Statute, Intituled, <hi>An Act for admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> the ſeventh Year of King <hi>James, That it ſhall and may be lawful,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And for any two Juſtices of the Peace, within any County, City or Towne Corporate, whereof one to be of the Quorum, to require any perſon or perſons, of the age of eighteen years or above, under the degree of a Baron or Baroneſs, to take the ſaid Oath.</hi> By which it is manifeſt, that no one Juſtice hath power to tender the Oath to any: And if it be no ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Law, it is no denial in Law, though the Priſoner do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to take it. For if one Juctice will be ſo hardy as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any to take the Oath contrary to Law, yet none that are conſcientious dare to be ſo wicked, as to take it from him whom the Law doth not intitle and impower to miniſter the ſame, unleſſe he will forſwear himſelf; for he that taketh the Oath, muſt ſwear amongſt other things, that it is lawfully mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to him, as appears in theſe expreſs words mentioned in the Oath it ſelf, <hi>Which I acknowledge by good and full Authority to be lawfully miniſtred unto me,</hi> &amp;c. When one Juſtice by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath no more authority than hath a Collier; and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome have been committed two or three times within this twelve moneths, for refuſing (as they call it) to take the Oath, when they were never required to take it by any lawful Authority. And at this day, ſeveral lie in Goal, and have done ſome moneths, whoſe perſons were ſeized con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the Kings Proclamation, as above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, for refuſing the Oath, as they are not aſhamed to ſay, and to charge them with in their Mittimus, when they never at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time of their commitment, were required to take it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their own Law, which they make no conſcience to break, though they cry out againſt others ſo much for the breach of. And further, though they ſay they are Chriſtians, the very Heathens may riſe up in judgement againſt them; For they would ſuffer <hi>Paul</hi> to ſpeak for himſelf in his own defence, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.39, 40. <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.10. But theſe men that ſay they are Chriſtians and Miniſters of Juſtice, will not ſuffer any of theſe ſober men they thus perſecute, to ſpeak for themſelves, not ſo much, hardly, as to give a reaſon why they cannot Swear.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48684:5"/>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, when in time of Seſſions they are called before their Tribunal, where though they deſire and intreat them to let them know what they had been kept in Priſon for, or what they or any other had againſt them; they, nor no man elſe can charge them with ought that they had done againſt the Law; which being ſo, they might hope to be heard, and thoſe Abuſes redreſſed; but there they can as little be heard alſo, nor no notice taken by the Bench of the Illegal proceedings of thoſe men called Juſtices; but in ſtead of <hi>Judgement behold Oppreſſion,</hi> and in the place of <hi>Righteouſneſſe behold a Cry,</hi> Iſa. 5.7. For when at the time of the Goal Delivery (as they call it) they ought by Law, and according to their Oathes, do right impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially to all free born <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> that is, let every one ſpeak freely for himſelf, in the face of the Countrey, that all may know his Guilt, if Guilty, or his Innocency if Innocent; and if nothing be found againſt them, by ſuch proof or ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent witneſs as the Law requires in ſuch caſes; they are ſworn to deliver them, and to do them right anſwerable to the wrongs they have ſuſtained by thoſe Mercenary Souldiers, that ſeize them contrary to Law and the Kings Proclamation, and thoſe unjuſt men, called Juſtices, for their falſe Impriſoning them; or at leaſt to leave both Souldiers and Juſtices open to the Law; which could honeſt men have the benefit of, againſt theſe Tyrants, it would ſufficiently repaire them. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let them not think, to excuſe themſelves by tendring the Oath of Obedience to them, againſt whom they can charge no matter of Fact: for it is neither Reaſon, Law nor Equity, that men ſhould lie in Priſon ſeveral moneths, as many have done in <hi>New-gate,</hi> and elſewhere, and no Crime committed by them, nor none accuſing them of any; that they ſhould then have the Oath tendred to enſnare them, and hold them faſt. For if it be a fault in Law to refuſe the Oath, when ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in Court, the fault was but then contracted; all the former Impriſonment, by their own proceedings appears to be manifeſtly falſe. And this is all the Juſtice they can have, <hi>Will you Swear, if you will not, you ſhall lie in Priſon ſtill.</hi> Thus is <hi>Judgement turned away backwards, and Juſtice ſtandeth afarre off: For Truth is fallen in the Streets, and Equity cannot enter: Yea
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48684:6"/>Truth faileth, and he that departeth from Iniquity, maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a prey;</hi> (or as it may be read, <hi>is accounted Mad,</hi> or <hi>a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick.) and the Lord ſaw it, and it diſpleaſed him, that there was no Judgement,</hi> Iſa. 59.14, 15.</p>
            <p>The Lord God without doubt ſits in Heaven and ſeeth their proceedings, who ſaith to them, <hi>How long will ye Judge unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and accept the Perſons of the wicked: Defend the poor and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, do Juſtice to the afflicted and needy, deliver the poor and needy, rid them out of the hands of the wicked,</hi> Pſal. 82.2, 3, 4. But ſurely, <hi>they have not God in all their thoughts.</hi> For it may be ſaid of ſuch, as the Lord ſaid by the Prophet <hi>Amos, They turn Judgement to Wormwood, and leave off Righteouſneſs in the Earth,</hi> Amos 5.7. And again, <hi>For behold the Lord command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and he will ſmite the great houſe with breaches, and the little houſe with clefts; Shall Horſes run upon the Rock? will one plow there with Oxen? for ye have turned Judgement into Gall, and the fruit of Righteouſneſs into Hemlock,</hi> Amos 6.11, 12. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they may ſay, in their hearts, <hi>The Lord will not do good, neither will be do evil,</hi> Zeph. 1.12. Yet let them know, he that ſits in Heaven <hi>ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion; he ſhall ſpeak to them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> Pſal. 2.4, 5. Therefore, <hi>Wo unto them that decree unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous decrees, and that write grievouſneſs which they have preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, to turn aſide the needy from Judgement, and to take away the right from the poor of my people,</hi> Iſa. 10.1.2. Little do theſe unjuſt men know, who thus pervert the Law, what woes and judgements hang over their heads, for their cruelty to the Lords People. The Word of the Lord ſhall ſurely be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and though he ſuffer the wicked for a time to afflict his People, yet, <hi>The Rod of the Wicked ſhall not reſt upon the Lot of the Righteous,</hi> Pſal. 125.3. And though for a time, <hi>the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed may ſpring as graſs, and all the workers of iniquity do flouriſh,</hi> (and tread upon the necks of the godly) <hi>it is that they ſhould be deſtroyed,</hi> Pſal. 92.7. For the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, and it ſhall certainly come to paſſe: For ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will undoe all that afflict thee, and I will ſave her that halteth, and gather her that was driven out; and I will get them praiſe and fame in every Land, where they have been put to ſhame,</hi> Zeph. 3.19.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48684:6"/>Oh that theſe men that perſecute the Lords people would break off their ſins of Tyranny, Oppreſſion, and Injuſtice, before the Decree be gone forth againſt them, by righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Thus having given an account to the World, of the unjuſt and Tyrannical proceedings againſt the peaceable of the Land; I ſhall now give (becauſe they are not ſuffered to ſpeak for themſelves) the Reaſons why they cannot take the Oath of Obedience, as I have collected from them in my frequent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with them. For the refuſing of which (as their Enemies, who are their Judges ſay) they lie in ſtinking Goals, deprived of the comfortable ſociety of their dear Relations, which God and Nature alloweth them; and made thereby un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of making ſuch good proviſion for them, as their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities call for; <hi>Chooſing rather,</hi> with Moſes, <hi>to ſuffer afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou with the People of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; knowing in themſelves that they have in heaven a better and more enduring ſubſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="reasons">
               <head>The Reaſons are as followeth.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>First,</hi> Becauſe it is a Promiſary Oath. Now Oathes of ſuch a kind are forbidden by Chriſt, <hi>the Prince of the Kings of the Earth,</hi> Rev. 1.5. Who onely is head of the Church, the great and onely Law-giver, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.22. <hi>James</hi> 4.12. That it is an Oath of ſuch a kind, is manifeſt to all that read it. That ſuch Oaths are forbidden by Chriſt, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>But I ſay unto you, Swear not at all,</hi> &amp;c. From which place I know that many ſay, <hi>That Chriſt forbids Swearing vainly,</hi> and <hi>Swearing by Creatures,</hi> and the like, and doth not forbid Swearing of any kind, provided it be by the Lord, and ſolemnly done.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt forbids in that place vain Swearing in common talk, or communication, and Swearing by Creatures though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſolemnly performed, is true: But that this is not all that is forbidden is as true: For Chriſt forbids ſome kind of Swearing that was in the time of <hi>Moſes</hi> approved, as appears in the 33. <hi>verſ. Ye have heard, that it hath been ſaid to them of old time, thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform unto the Lord thine Oathes.</hi> Which was no gloſs, as ſome would have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48684:7"/>it, but by the Lord required, that if a man Swore an Oath, or Vowed a Vow, unto which he was not bound by any Law of God to do, but was at Liberty in; whether they would or would not Swear, yet having ſworn, the Lord requires he ſhould perform his Oath, by which he hath bound his Soul. <hi>Num.</hi> 30.2. <hi>If a man Vow a Vow unto the Lord, or Swear an Oath to bind his Soul with a bond, he ſhall not break</hi> (or profane) <hi>his Word, he ſhall do according to all that proceedeth out of his mouth.</hi> Now ſaith Chriſt, <hi>it was ſaid, thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but thou ſhalt perform unto the Lord thine Oathes; but I ſay, Swear not at all:</hi> As much as if Chriſt ſhould ſay, though it was your Liberty, and no Sin, to promiſe and bind your Soul to the performance of ſomething or other, you ſwear to do, provided you break not your word; yet henceforth, I ſay, that am the Son, and impowred by my Father, now to be the Law-giver; that upon no ſuch account, or in ſuch a kind you Swear, by which you bind your Souls by promiſe to perform this or that. But in ſuch caſes, <hi>let your Yea be Yea, and your Nay Nay.</hi> Thus its evident, that Chriſt forbids ſuch kind of Swearing as was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by <hi>Moſes</hi> in Old Times, <hi>viz.</hi> Voluntary, Promiſary Swearing, and not vain Swearing only, in common talk, nor Swearing by Creatures; both which were forbidden by them of Old Time, as alſo falſe Swearing: For the which there might be a Cloud of Witneſſes brought. But if any ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and ſay, that Chriſt indeed doth forbid Promiſary Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but it is ſuch onely, as is raſh and inconſiderable. To ſuch it is anſwered, That raſh and inconſiderable Swearing and Vowing, was diſapproved by them of Old Time, aſwel as vain and falſe Swearing, and may be ſummed up in the number of the reſt of Swearings that are forbidden, and were ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by them of Old Time, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.10. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.2. <hi>Zech.</hi> 5.3, 4. But further, either (Chriſt forbids in ſaying, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> Mat. 5.34. and <hi>James</hi> 5.12. <hi>Above all things my brethren Swear not,</hi> &amp;c.) all manner or kind of Swearing, of what ſort ſoever, or elſe he forbids all of one kind; elſe what ſignify theſe words, <hi>not at all,</hi> the terme being univerſal, and muſt wholly prohibit, either, as is ſaid, all kind of Swearing, or all of that kind it relates to; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48684:7"/>while it can be proved that there is a deſtinction to be made, by allowance from Chriſt, between Promiſary and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſary Swearing, its concluded, that Chriſt forbids all Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that kind, to wit, Promiſary; And therefore they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>Second</hi> Reaſon is, Becauſe they are Chriſt's liege People, He is their King, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.4. <hi>King of Nations, fer.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.1, 2, 3. And <hi>King of kings,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.16. They ſtand bound, and engaged to Chriſt, to ſerve, obey, and glorifie him, to own and ſubmit to his Lawes and Commands, and not mans Traditions; for he hath in his rich and free Love to them, given himſelf for them, that he might purchaſe and buy them with the price of his precious blood, to the end he might be Lord and King over them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9. And that they ſhould ſerve Him and not men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.23. Now if they take the Oath of Allegiance, they become bound to obey the King in what he Commands them, whether his Commands agree with Chriſt's or no. For if they Swear, they muſt perform, <hi>Num.</hi> 30.2. If it be Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, <hi>That, that doth not follow.</hi> It's Anſwered, <hi>It will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the enſuing Reaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe he that takes the Oath of Allegiance, ſwears and bindes his Soul (though not expreſly, yet impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly) to obey the King in whatſoever he Commands them to do, in things Spiritual as well as Temporal, for he is ſworn to obey the King indifinitely; for by the Oath he hath no diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation to refuſe obedience to any Command of the King what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
               <p>Be not deceived, the Oath excepts nor excludes no one Command, of what nature or kind ſoever it be; but as is above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, they that Swear, Swear indifinitely, <hi>That they will bear Faith and true Obedience to the King:</hi> The King Commands Obedience to him, according to his Laws, which he is ſworn to maintain; his Laws they Command in things Spiritual as well as otherwiſe, as might abundantly be ſhewed; And therefore they cannot take the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Becauſe he that Sweares Obedience to the King, muſt be forſworn if he afterwads frequent Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48684:8"/>as formerly, to Serve and Worſhip God according to the Command of the Spirit, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25. and come not to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer; for the King hath forbid the one, and the Law Commands the other. Now the plain truth is, they cannot own Common Prayer, nor the Lordly Biſhops, come Life come Death, nor none of their Rubbiſh whatſoever; Becauſe they are not the Miniſters of Chriſt, nor their Wayes the Wayes of Chriſt, but their own humane Inventions and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. For where was ſuch a thing appointed by Chriſt, or practiſed by his Miniſters in the Primitive times, as Common Prayer, which is full of <hi>Babling and vain Repetitions?</hi> contrary to <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>What is it then, I will pray with the Spirit, and will pray with Underſtanding alſo: I will Sing with the Spirit, and I will Sing with the Underſtanding alſo,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.15. But who among them can be ſaid to Pray with the Spirit, that Pray out of the <hi>Engliſh Mas Book?</hi> and that hears them ſing Prick-Song, like Fidlers in their Fantaſtick garb of white Frocks, or Surplices, their Hoods and Tippets, and ſuch like Fopperies; their Organs, Sackbuts, Cornets, Houboys, and ſuch like; more like the Worſhip that <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> commanded the <hi>Three Children, Dan.</hi> 3.14, 15. than any Chriſt commanded under, or in the time of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: Therefore they cannot take the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Becauſe he that Swears Allegiance, is Sworn to maintain the Kings Dignity to the utmoſt of his power. By which it is evident, that the Oath cannot be kept in yeelding (as ſome ſay they are onely bound to) paſſive Obedience, but he muſt alſo maintain the Kings Dignities, ſaith the Oath, now the Dignity of the King, is not onely to be Supream in point of things Temporal, but in things Spiritual alſo; the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that the Law gives him that dignity, to be Supream in Spiritual things and cauſes, as well as Temporal. See the Oath of Supremacy, in a Statute, Intituled, <hi>An Act for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring to the Crown the ancient Jurisdiction;</hi> Made in the firſt Year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> Some part of which Act, for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſatisfaction, is inſerted, as followeth:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And that alſo it may pleaſe your Highueſs, that it maybe eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that ſuch Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48684:8"/>Priviledges, Superiorities, and Preheminencies Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or Eccleſiaſtical, as by any Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Power or Authority hath heretofore been, or lawfully may be exerciſed or uſed, for the viſitation of the Eccleſiaſtical State and Perſons, and for Reformation, Order and Correction of the ſame, and of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Errors, Hereſies, Schiſmes, Abuſes, Offences, Contempts and Enormities, ſhall for ever by the Authority of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, be united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>See alſo a Statute, <hi>Anno,</hi> 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 12. Let the Reader take notice, that theſe things are not cited or ſaid, to ſhew that not the King, but the Pope, or ſome man elſe is Supream Head of the Church, for ſuch a thing is abhorred by them, they utterly diſ-claiming and diſ-owning any Power or Authority the Pope hath, and would rejoyce to ſee the utter deſolation of him and all that Hierarchy. They knowing that no man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving upon the Earth hath that dignity; but it is Chriſts, to whom <hi>All Power in Heaven and in Earth is committed,</hi> by the Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28, 18. Whence then it's clear, That he that Swears, is not onely bound by Oath, to yeeld actual Obedience to the Kings Commands, in falling in with Common Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as above; but he is bound by Oath, with a Sword in his hand to maintain his Dignity in point of Spirituals, as well as any other, againſt all attempts made againſt it; Therefore they cannot take the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Becauſe he that Swears, is ignorant of what he binds his Soul to, which to do is ſin, <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.4, 5. <hi>If a Soul Swear, pronouncing with his Lips, to do evil or to do good, what ſoever it be, that a man ſhall pronounce with an Oath, and it be hid from him, when he knoweth of it, then he ſhall be guilty in one of theſe; and it ſhall be when he ſhall be guilty in one of theſe things, that he ſhall confeſs that he hath ſinned in that thing.</hi> Now, that whoſoever takes the Oath of Obedience, muſt be ignorant of what he binds his Soul to, is evident; becauſe, he binds his Soul not onely to the King in being, to whom he Swears Allegiance, but to his Succeſſors alſo: And if it were poſſible for a man to know, what the King now in being would command in all points: yet it is impoſſible to know what his Succeſſors may;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48684:9"/>For were the preſent King <hi>a man after God's own heart,</hi> as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was; yet who knowes but he that ſucceeds him may intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Popery, as Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, did? Now he that takes the Oath, binds his Soul to obey thoſe that ſhall ſucceed whether Papiſt or Pagan, as much as the King that is in preſent being; Therefore they cannot take the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Becauſe they cannot Swear upon the true Faith of a Chriſtian, as they are enjoyned in the Oath to do. For as much as in part or in whole they are ignorant, if not at preſent, yet for the future, what it is they are bound by Oath to.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Becauſe, he that takes the Oath of Allegiance, muſt Swear by the true Faith of a Chriſtian; now to Swear by the Faith of a Chriſtian, is to Swear by ſomething that is not God, contrary to <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.2. and <hi>James</hi> 5.12. Therefore they cannot take the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Becauſe, they that take the Oath, muſt Swear they take it heartily, willingly and truly; which no man can do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he have great clearneſs in himſelf by undeniable teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from the Word of Life, that the things he Swears to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, are uncontrovertably his Liberty, if not his Duty.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>Tenthly,</hi> Becauſe, God expreſly Commandeth him that will Swear and bind his Soul by an Oath, to <hi>Swear in Truth, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and in Judgement,</hi> Jer. 4.2. which no man can do, if igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as above ſaid.</p>
               <p>Theſe are their Reaſons, or at leaſt ſome of them; beſides all which, they are in doubt in other things relating to the Oath; In order unto which, for ſatisfaction, they propound theſe <hi>Queries</hi> following;</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Firſt.</label> 
                  <hi>Whether all ſuch that Swear Allegiance, who have been Actors in the late War, in Perſon, Eſtate, or otherwiſe; do not</hi> Build again the things they Deſtroyed? <hi>and whether ſo to do be no Sin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Secondly.</label> 
                  <hi>Whether all ſuch as have Sworn, or ſhall Swear Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48684:9"/>who aſſiſted the Parliament in the War, either in Perſon or Eſtate, do not openly proclaim themſelves, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge upon Oath to the World, that they are Trattors, Thieves, and Murtherers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Thirdly.</label> 
                  <hi>Whether all ſuch as have Sworn, or ſhall Swear, who have ſet days apart, either in publick or in private, to Faſt and Pray for the good Succeſs of the Parliament; do not manifeſt themſelves to be notorious Diſſemblers, and God-Mockers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Fourthly.</label> 
                  <hi>Whether ſuch who ſhall Swear, as aboveſaid, who have kept days of Thanks-giving, (when any Victory hath been obtained) to praiſe the Lord for his wonderful goodneſs and to ſpeak of the might of his terrible Acts; do not by Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, openly throw dirt in the face of God, and conclude that to be of the Devil, that they then ſaid was the glorious Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Majeſty, and his wonderous Works?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Fifthly.</label> 
                  <hi>Whether a man, though he make a hundred Exceptions if poſſible, againſt ſome things in the Oath, and leave be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him ſo to do, and he take it after the Exceptions be made; doth not Swear (notwithſtanding his Exceptions) according to the plain and expreſſe Letter of it, and ſo make void his former Exceptions? foraſmuch as he Swears ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe expreſs words, (viz.)</hi> And all theſe things, I do plainly and ſincerely acknowledge and Swear, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe expreſs words by me ſpoken, and according to the plain and common ſence and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the ſame words, without equivocation, or mental evaſion, or ſecret reſervation whatſoever.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48684:10"/>
               <p>Thus may all men ſee, that theſe men do not lie in Priſon out of any ſelf-willedneſs (as ſome wickedly ſay they do) but meerly upon the account of Chriſt, and a good Conſcience, which they dare not violate or make ſhipwrack of, in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſteps of others; neither dare they engage in any thing diſhonourable to Chriſt their King, which they conceive Swearing Allegiance to any man upon the Earth will be; their refuſing the Oath, is not without ground: Their Reaſons are prevailing to them, and may be to others, did they duly weigh and conſider them: if any can take them off by the word of Truth, and right Reaſon, they will do God ſervice, and them alſo, in being inſtrumental to open the Priſon doors; for were they ſatisfied, then would they Swear, and obtain their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and acknowledge their miſtake, as I am truly and well perſwaded of them; but till then, their Conſcience and the Honour of Chriſt (who is precious to them) is more than ſtone-Walls, iron Grates, Locks and Bolts, to hold them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not their Perſecutors think to eſcape the dreadfull Judgements of God if they repent not of their wickedneſs, and hard ſpeeches that they have ungodlily ſpoken againſt them; For in touching them that fear the Lord (and an Oath) they touch the apple of Gods eye, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8. <hi>He reproved Kings for their ſake; ſaying, touch not mine Anointed, nor do my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets no harm,</hi> Pſal. 105.14, 15. The Lord will one day <hi>ariſe and have mercy upon Sion; ſo the Heathen ſhall fear the Name of the Lord, and all she Kings of the Earth thy glory,</hi> Pſal. 102.14, 15. <hi>For he hath looked down from the height of his Sanctuary, from Heaven did the Lord behold the Earth, to hear the groaning of the Priſoner, to looſe thoſe that are appointed to death,</hi> Verſ. 19, 20. <hi>The humble ſhall ſee this and be glad, your heart ſhall live that ſeek God, for the Lord heareth the poor, and deſpiſeth not his Priſoners,</hi> Pſ. 69.32, 33. Oh happy men are they that thus ſuffer reproach and bonds for the Name of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14. Yea, <hi>Bleſſed are</hi> they, <hi>when men revile</hi> them, <hi>and perſecute</hi> them, <hi>and ſhall ſay all manner of evil</hi> of them, <hi>falſly, for</hi> his <hi>ſake,</hi> Mat. 5.11. as that they are <hi>Phanaticks</hi> or <hi>Mad-men,</hi> for ſo ſaid they of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 10.20. <hi>And many of them ſaid, he hath a Devil, and is mad, why hear ye him?</hi> That they have turned the World upſide-down,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48684:10"/>and do things contrary to the Decrees of the King; ſaying, that <hi>there is another King, one Jeſus.</hi> So ſaid thoſe wicked Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Gods People of Old, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.6, 7. That <hi>they are Peſtilent fellows, and movers of Sedition;</hi> So ſaid <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Orator, of <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 24.5. That they are Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, and what not, as ſaith the Pope, and <hi>Englands</hi> Lordly Biſhops.</p>
               <p>Well, notwithſtanding let them <hi>rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is</hi> their <hi>reward in Heaven; for ſo perſecuted they the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> Chriſt, and his Servants, <hi>that were before them,</hi> Mat. 5.12. It being an evident token of <hi>Perdition</hi> to their adverſaries, but of <hi>Salvation</hi> to them, and that of God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.28. Let them therefore be encouraged to ſtand faſt, and keep their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, and not touch with any of the filthy Abominations of the times to obtain their Liberty: God will one day make up all their loſſes, and ſufficiently repair them. <hi>For if they ſuffer with Chriſt, they ſhall reign with him,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.12. <hi>Walk not then, ye</hi> Priſoners of Hope, <hi>nor ye</hi> Saints at Liberty, <hi>in the way of this People; Say ye not a Confederacy to all them, to whom this People ſhall ſay a Confederacy, neither fear ye their fear, nor be afraid; but ſanctifie the Lord of Hoſts himſelf, and let him be your fear, and let him be your dread; and he ſhall be for a Sanctuary,</hi> Iſa. 8.11, 12, 13. Be ye waiting upon the Lord, until the day that <hi>he riſe up to the Prey, for his determination is to gather the Nations, that he may aſſemble the Kingdoms, to poure upon them his indignation, even all his fierce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; For all the Earth ſhall be devoured with the fire of his Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie: for then will he turn to the People of pure Language, that they may all call upon the Name of the Lord, to ſerve him with one conſent,</hi> Zeph. 3.8, 9. <hi>Wait</hi> (I ſay) <hi>on the Lord, and keep his way, and he ſhall exalt thee, to inherit the Land, when the wicked are cut off; Thou ſhalt ſee it,</hi> Pſal. 37.34.</p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
